Guide to the Dwight and Ferris Family Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Dwight and Ferris family papers
1711-1951
GEN MSS 468
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
3.18
(5 boxes) + 1 portfolio
The papers span the dates 1711-1951, and the bulk of material concerns three individuals: Timothy Dwight (1694-1771), Theodore Dwight (1796-1866), and Eleanor Augusta Ferris. The papers of Timothy Dwight document events of Dummer's War and the management of Fort Dummer in 1724-25, as well as his later work as a surveyor and Judge during the period of dispute over boundaries and administration of the New Hampshire Grants. The papers of Theodore Dwight include a diary or notebook containing manuscript drafts of his writings as well as accounts of some of his travels, a manuscript of a lesson book for young school children with instructions for teachers, one letter from Garibaldi, and personal documents and manuscripts. The papers of Eleanor Augusta Ferris consist chiefly of correspondence from Ada Galsworthy, but also include letters from contributors to "The Villager" and from family members. The collection also contains other papers of the Dwight and Ferris families, including letters, documents, and genealogies of the Dwight Family, a few papers of Theodore Dwight (1764-1846), and photographs of the Ferris family from about the 1870s to the 1940s.
Dwight family
Drake, Joseph Rodman, 1795-1820 ( Culprit fay)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Eleanor Augusta Ferris, Mary Dwight Ferris, and Isabel Stuart Ferris, 1929-1962.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Restricted fragile material in Port 105. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Associated Materials
Related material can be found in the Dwight Family Papers, 1713-1937, located in Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library, and in the Dwight Family Papers, 1789-1966 at the New York Public Library. It is possible that other related material may be found at the New-York Historical Society.
DWIGHT FAMILY
The following chart shows the direct line of descent from the first Dwight to settle in America to the Ferris sisters, who donated these papers to the library. For more detailed genealogical information, see the Appendix, the Dwight Family chart in Box 5, Folder 101, and the summary in Box 4, Folder 95. Names of family members particularly well represented in this collection are in italics.
John Dwight m. Hannah (they arrived from England ca. 1635)
--Timothy Dwight (1629-1717) m. Anna Flint (3rd of six wives)
----Nathaniel Dwight (1666-1711) m. (1693) Mehitable Partridge
------ Timothy Dwight (1694-1771) m. (1716) Experience King
--------Timothy Dwight (1726-1777) m. Mary Edwards (1734-1807)
----------Theodore Dwight (1764-1836) m. (1792) Abigail Alsop
------------ Theodore Dwight (1796-1866) m. (1827) Ellen Boyd
---------------Augusta Moore Dwight m. Sherwood Bissell Ferris
------------------ Eleanor Augusta Ferris (b. 1872)
------------------Mary Dwight Ferris
------------------Isabel Stuart Ferris
------------------Anna Edwards Ferris m. (ca. 1900) Charles Ingalls Marvin
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTES
Timothy Dwight (1694-1771) was the son of Nathaniel Dwight (1666-1711) of Northampton, Massachusetts. As an officer in the Massachusetts Militia, he built and commanded Fort Dummer during the Indian conflict known as Dummer's War, circa 1723-26. He rose in rank from Lieutenant in 1724 to Colonel by the 1740s, by which time he had moved from Fort Dummer back to Northampton, and become a lawyer and surveyor. In the 1750s he served as Judge of Probate for Hampshire County, Massachusetts.
His only son, Timothy Dwight (1726-1777), was born at Fort Dummer. Like his father, the younger Timothy Dwight served in the Massachusetts Militia. He married Mary Edwards, daughter of the theologian Jonathan Edwards, and lived in Northampton for most of his life. He remained loyal to the Crown during the American Revolution and died in Natchez, Mississippi.
Theodore Dwight, Sr. (1764-1846), son of Timothy Dwight (1726-1834) and brother of Yale President Timothy Dwight (1752-1817), was born in Northampton but lived for most of his adult life in Hartford, Connecticut, and New York City. He was a lawyer, newspaper editor, member of the Connecticut State Council, and a member of Congress in 1806-07. He served as Secretary of the Hartford Convention in 1814, and wrote a history of that event.
His son, Theodore Dwight, Jr. (1796-1866), born in Hartford, was an author and educator. He graduated from Yale College in 1814, and studied theology with his uncle, Yale President Timothy Dwight (1752-1817), but never became a minister. On his first trip to Italy in 1820, he established a lasting friendship with the revolutionary Giuseppe Garibaldi, whose autobiography he translated for publication in 1859. After marrying Ellen Boyd in 1827, he settled in Brooklyn, New York, where he worked for his father as an editorial assistant, and wrote many books and articles on education, travel, history, linguistics, and ethnography. He was involved in several scholarly and philanthropic societies, and was an active promoter of the settlement of Kansas as a Free State in the 1850s. (For a more detailed biography, see Box 4, Folder 85.)
Eleanor Augusta Ferris (b. 1872) was Theodore Dwight, Jr.'s granddaughter. She edited a periodical called "The Villager," begun in 1929 and published by the Bronxville Women's Club, of Bronxville, New York, where she lived with her sisters Mary and Isabel. Her own short stories also appeared in "The Villager." Among her many literary friends were John and Ada Galsworthy, whom she met circa 1920; she maintained a correspondence with Ada Galsworthy throughout the rest of her life.
Scope and Contents
The Dwight and Ferris family papers span the years 1711 to 1951, and the bulk of the material concerns three individuals: Timothy Dwight (1694-1771), Theodore Dwight, Jr. (1796-1866), and Eleanor Augusta Ferris. The collection is organized into five series: Papers of Timothy Dwight (1694-1771), Papers of Theodore Dwight (1796-1866), Other Dwight Family Papers, Papers of Eleanor Augusta Ferris, and Other Ferris Family Papers.
Series I, Papers of Timothy Dwight (1694-1771) is organized into two subseries: Fort Dummer Papers and Other Papers. It consists chiefly of correspondence and papers documenting Dwight's command of Fort Dummer in 1724-25, but also includes correspondence from 1731-63 that documents his work as a surveyor and a judge. Most of the papers in this series were, at the time of acquisition, glued into a book inscribed "Fort Dummer Papers from Theodore Dwight's Collection, 62 Harris St., Brooklyn." They have been removed and foldered individually, both for their protection and to facilitate logical arrangement. In order to maintain the integrity of that collection, all of the papers from the book are included in this series, including one letter which may be to Timothy Dwight (1726-1777). The numbers on the papers, usually in the upper left hand corner, refer to their arrangement in the book (there were no numbers 6 or 12 at the time of acquisition). The boards of the book can be found in Series II, Papers of Theodore Dwight (1796-1866).
Fort Dummer was built in 1724 as a scouting station during the conflict between English settlers and Abenaki Indians known as Dummer's War, 1723-1726, sometimes also called Grey Lock's War or Lovewell's War. It was the first fortification on the English frontier, and was located on the West bank of the Connecticut River near the present site of Brattleboro, Vermont. It is sometimes referred to in the papers as "the fort above Northfield," "the fort in the Long Meadow," or "the Block House." Papers concerning Fort Dummer document events, expeditions, and general management of the fort from January 1724 to October 1725. They include a plan for construction of the fort in January of 1724 and a photostatic copy of a muster-roll for the Company of Captain Timothy Dwight, circa 1725. Names of Militiamen and Mohawk Indians garrisoned at the fort can also be found in the correspondence, which includes three outgoing letters from Dwight, as well as letters from Lieutenant Governor of Massachusetts William Dummer, Dwight's commanding officer Colonel John Stoddard, Captain Samuel Partridge, and other officers stationed along the Western frontier. There are also copies of two letters from Colonel John Schuyler in Albany, one of which contains a detailed report of failed peace negotiations held in Canada in August of 1724.
The later papers of Timothy Dwight (1694-1771), 1731-63, document his work as a surveyor and Judge of Probate for Hampshire County, Massachusetts during the period of dispute over the boundaries of New Hampshire and Massachusetts, which was concentrated particularly on the Northfield and Fort Dummer region. Some of the letters document the establishment of townships in the New Hampshire Grants to the West of Fort Dummer, and the administration of land grants in Massachusetts. Correspondents from this period include Massachusetts Governors Jonathan Belcher and Thomas Pownall; there is also an undated letter from New Hampshire Governor Benning Wentworth.
Series II, Papers of Theodore Dwight (1796-1866), consists of correspondence, writings, documents, and a few other papers. The writings include a manuscript for a lesson book for young children, with instructions to teachers and small illustrations, and a diary or notebook covering the years 1820 to 1865. The diary/notebook contains entries from the beginning of Dwight's journey to Italy in 1820, copied from another volume and corrected in pencil, as well as entries made in Italy, Ecuador, and in New York in later life; translations of articles and other notes concerning education systems in several European countries; a series of entries from 1833-34 titled "Diary of a Sabbath School;" drafts of short pieces about evangelization of Italians, Spanish, and Jews in America; an outline and draft first chapter titled "The School Teacher's Guide," with an outline titled "The Sunday School Guide" inserted loose; and copies of outgoing letters in [shorthand?] from 1851-1865. Other papers include Dwight's Yale Diploma and other certificates, a letter from him to "Dear Friends," into which he copied his journal from a sea voyage in 1817, and one letter from Garibaldi. Also included are his wife Ellen Boyd's autograph album, begun before she was married, which includes a sketch of Newstead Abbey, seat of Lord Byron, and her manuscript copy of Joseph Rodman Drake's poem "The Culprit Fay," inscribed with her husband's name.
Series III, Other Dwight Family Papers, contains a genealogical chart showing six generations of male descendents of John and Hannah Dwight, and letters and papers of various members of the family. These include two letters to Theodore Dwight (1764-1846), one of which is from Connecticut Governor Oliver Wolcott, the other from a Timothy Dwight concerning the book about the Hartford Convention; two letters to Mary Edwards Dwight from her son Sereno Dwight in Jamaica; and a Northampton church record of a dispute between an unspecified Mr. Dwight and Decon Shelding in 1711.
Series IV, Papers of Eleanor Augusta Ferris, is organized into two subseries: Correspondence and John Galsworthy Ephemera. The bulk of the correspondence is from Ada Galsworthy between 1921 and 1951. Most of the remaining correspondence is from contributors to "The Villager," but there are a few letters concerning the life and work of her grandfather, Theodore Dwight (1796-1866), and one concerning the papers of Timothy Dwight (1694-1771) given to the library (see: Series I). There is also a letter from the New-York Historical Society which seems to concern a gift of Dwight Family material to that institution.
Series V, Other Ferris Family Papers, consists chiefly of photographs taken between the 1870s and about 1940, but also includes genealogical notes made by one of the Ferris sisters about the Ferris and Whiting families, and a summary of their Dwight lineage written for the library at the time the papers of Timothy Dwight (1694-1771) were given. Also included are postcards received by Mary and Isabel Ferris.
Appendix: Dwight Family Genealogy
The following chart is intended to serve as a reference tool for this collection, and is not a complete Dwight family tree. It includes only the descendents of Nathaniel Dwight (1666-1711) whose names are present in the collection. Because of the number of Dwights in the extended family named Timothy, Henry, Samuel, Jonathan, Nathaniel and Joseph, it is impossible in a few cases to determine with which family member a particular letter or document corresponds. For the same reason, it is possible that some material in the collection may pertain to members of other branches of the family. For more detailed genealogical information about the Dwight family, see the chart in Box 5, folder 101.
John Dwight (d. 1659-60) m. Hannah (they arrived from England ca. 1635)
--Timothy Dwight (1629-1717) m. Anna Flint (3rd of his six wives)
----(Other children)
----Nathaniel Dwight (1666-1711) m. (1693) Mehitable Partridge
-------Samuel Dwight
-----------Daniel Dwight
-----------(Other children)
-------Daniel Dwight
-----------Daniel Dwight
-----------Samuel Dwight
-----------John Dwight
-----------Nathaniel Dwight
-----------(Other children)
-------Jonathan Dwight
-----------Jonathan Dwight
-------Nathaniel Dwight
-----------Elihu Dwight
-----------(Other children)
-------Timothy Dwight (1694-1771) m. (1716) Experience King
-----------Timothy Dwight (1726-1777) m. Mary Edwards (1734-1807)
----------------Timothy Dwight (1752-1817)
----------------Sereno Dwight m. Cynthia
----------------Jonathan Edwards Dwight
----------------Nathaniel Dwight
----------------Henry Edwin Dwight
----------------(Other children)
----------------Theodore Dwight (c1764-1836) m. (1792) Abigail Alsop
--------------------(Other children)
--------------------Theodore Dwight (1796-1866) m.(1827) Ellen Boyd
------------------------(Other children?)
------------------------Rebecca Dwight
------------------------Augusta Moore Dwight m. Sherwood Bissell Ferris
----------------------------Anna Edwards Ferris m. Charles Ingalls Marvin
----------------------------------Sherwood Ferris Marvin (b. 1903)
----------------------------------Dwight Edwards Marvin (died in infancy)
----------------------------------Anne Edwards Marvin (b. 1911)
----------------------------Eleanor Augusta Ferris
----------------------------Mary Dwight Ferris
----------------------------Isabel Stuart Ferris
Note: the "Dwight Book" occasionally referred to in the papers can be found in Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library. The citation follows:
Dwight, Benjamin Woodbridge. The History of the Descendents of John Dwight, of Dedham, Mass. New York: J. F. Trow & Son, printers, 1874.
Abenaki Indians; Early childhood education -- History; Eastern Indians, Wars with, 1722-1726; Mohawk Indians; Religious education of children -- United States; Voyages and travels; Fort Dummer (Vt.); Massachusetts -- Boundaries; Massachusetts -- History -- Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775; Land grants -- Vermont; Vermont -- History -- To 1791; Autograph albums; Diaries; Genealogies (histories); Passports; Dummer, William, 1677-1761; Dwight, Ellen Boyd; Dwight, Theodore, 1764-1846; Dwight, Theodore, 1796-1866; Dwight, Timothy, 1694-1771; Dwight, Timothy, 1726-1777; Ferris, Eleanor, 1872-; Ferris, Isabel Stuart; Ferris, Mary Dwight; Galsworthy, Ada, -1956; Galsworthy, John, 1867-1933; Garibaldi, Giuseppe, 1807-1882; Marvin, Anna Edwards Ferris; Partridge, Samuel; Pownall, Thomas, 1722-1805; Stoddard, John, 1681-1748; Dwight family; Farris family; Massachusetts. Militia
- Papers of Timothy Dwight (1694-1771), 1724-1763; Series I; 43
  - FORT DUMMER PAPERS
    Scope and Contents
    This subseries is organized under two headings: Correspondence and Other Fort Dummer Papers. Arrangement under each heading is chronological.
    Note: letters addressed to "Captain Dwight" have been filed as letters to Timothy Dwight, although it is possible that they were written to one of his brothers, who were also Captains.
    - Correspondence
      All correspondence is incoming unless otherwise noted.
      - Dummer, William, [1724?] (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - Greenleaf, Stephen, at Boston, 1724 Feb 15 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Partridge, Samuel, at Hatfield, 1724 Apr 24 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Doolittle, Benjamin, at Northfield, to Captain Dwight, with glossary of Indian words on verso, 1724 Jun 18 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - Dwight, Henry, at Hatfield, 1724 Jun 29 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - TD to Captain Eben Pomeroy at Northampton, from Fort Dummer, 1724 Jul 29 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Stoddard, J., at Northampton, 1724 Aug 6 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Winchel, Joseph, at Suffield, 1724 Aug 15 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Partridge, Samuel, at Hatfield, to Captains Wells, Williams, Kellogg, Dwight, and Billing, 1724 Aug 24 (Box 1, Folder 9)
        Contains a copy of a letter from Colonel John Schuyler, at Albany, 1724 Aug 17, to John Stoddard, which contains the report of a peace delegation sent to Canada
      - Partridge, Samuel, letter to Captains Wells, Williams, Masson, Pomery, and TD (Box 1, Folder 10)
        Contains copy of a letter from John Schuyler, at Albany, to Colonel Stoddard, 1724 Sep 8.
      - TD to Doctor [Hastings?], from Fort Dummer, 1725 Jan 9 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Stoddard, John, at Northampton, 1725 Feb 23 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Stoddard, John, at Northampton, 1725 Mar 16 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - Stoddard, John, at Hatfield, 1725 Apr 21 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Partridge, Samuel, at Hatfield, 1725 Jun 14 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - Hinsdell, Mehuman, of Deerfield, to Captains Benjamin Wright and TD (Box 1, Folder 16)
        Contains copy of letter from John Schuyler at Saratoga, 1725 Jun 12
      - Austin, Richard, at Suffield, 1725 Jun 15 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      - Wright, Benjamin, 1725 Jul 30 (Box 1, Folder 18)
        With "List of men that went with Captain Wright," addressed to William Dummer, [att?] Henry Dwight, Boston
      - Dummer, William, at Boston, 1725 Aug 4 (Box 1, Folder 19)
      - Partridge, Samuel, at Hatfield, 1725 Aug 11 (Box 1, Folder 20)
      - TD [to William Dummer], fragment, from Fort Dummer, 1725 Aug 23 (Box 1, Folder 21)
      - Stoddard, John, at Northampton, fragment, [1725?] Oct 25 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Other Fort Dummer Papers
      - Partridge, Samuel, at Northampton, list of men appointed to the company of Major John Stoddard, 1716 Mar 23 (Box 1, Folder 23)
      - Plan of the fort, signed by John Stoddard, Northampton, 1724 Jan 30 (Box 1, Folder 24)
      - Partridge, Samuel and John Stoddard, at Springfield, ALS to Jonathan Wells, Deerfield, 1724 May 18 (Box 1, Folder 25)
        Forwarded by Wells to Captain Nathaniel Dwight at Fort Dummer
      - Soldiers' Petition, to Dr. Thomas Hastings, Hatfield, fragment, 1724 Nov 16 (Box 1, Folder 26)
        Inscriptions on verso, and signature [?] of a Timothy Dwight
      - Photostatic copy of muster-roll, Company of Captian TD, [1725?] (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - OTHER PAPERS
    This subseries is organized under two headings: Correspondence and Notes. Arrangement is chronological.
    - Correspondence
      - Wentworth, B., to Captain Dwight, fragment (Box 1, Folder 28)
      - Russell, Samuel, at North Guilford, 1731 Mar 9 (Box 1, Folder 29)
      - [Belcher, J., at Boston, fragment], EMPTY FOLDER: item now stored in: Oversize, 1732 Jun 15 (Box 1, Folder [30])
        Related Archival Materials note
        See: folder 102
      - First Church of Christ, Springfield, LS to John Stoddard, Eben Pomeroy, and TD, 1735 Oct 8 (Box 1, Folder 31)
        Complaint signed by thirteen members of the church
      - Dwight, Jonathan, at Boston, 1748 Sep 21 (Box 1, Folder 32)
      - Hopkins, Samuel, at Sheffield, 1749 May 10 (Box 1, Folder 33)
      - Dwight, Samuel, at Somers, 1749 Aug 2 (Box 1, Folder 34)
      - Dwight, John, at Killingley [?], to Captain TD [1726-1777?], Northampton, 1751 Apr 5 (Box 1, Folder 35)
        Probably to the younger Captain TD (1726-1777)
      - Hopkins, Samuel, at Sheffield, 1751 Aug 9 (Box 1, Folder 36)
      - Dwight, Nathaniel, report and expense account for two journeys to survey land in the New Hampshire Grants, 1751 Nov 25 (Box 1, Folder 37)
        The journeys were made by order of Joseph Dwight, Edmund Quincy, and Timothy Dwight
      - King, Sara, plea to TD, Judge of Probate for Hampshire County, regarding "Letter of Administration", 1757 Mar 1 (Box 1, Folder 38)
      - Dwight, Samuel, memorandum regarding land in the New Hampshire Grants, 1757 Jul 16 (Box 1, Folder 39)
      - Pownall, Thomas, regarding "Letters of Administration", 1758 Apr 24 (Box 1, Folder 40)
      - Pownall, Thomas, fragment of letter containing instructions to TD and Dr. Perez Marsh, [1758] (Box 1, Folder 41)
      - Dwight, Jonathan, at Halifax, 2 ALS, 1763 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Notes
      - Leaf of paper inscribed "Timothy Dwight his book 1722", 1722 Jul (Box 1, Folder 43)
        On the verso are notes concerning a legal case between Samuel Smith and David King, undated.
- Papers of Theodore Dwight (1794-1866), 1814-1865; Series II; 10
  See also: Biographical sketch in Box 4, Folder 85
  - Autograph fragment to "Dear Friends," on board the Comet, sailing from New York, 1817 May 16-24 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Garibaldi, Giuseppe, ALS to TD, 1851 Feb 4 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Manuscript of a lesson book for school children, bound volume (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Diary/notebook, 1820-1865 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    With gaps; includes notes on European educational practices and evangelicism, copies of outgoing correspondence in [shorthand?], and draft of "The School Teacher's Guide;" with outline titled "The Sunday School Guide" inserted loose
  - [A.B. from Yale College], EMPTY FOLDER, item now stored in Oversize, 1814 Sep 14 (Box 2, Folder [48])
    See: folder 104
  - Certificate of membership in the Church of Christ, Yale College, manuscript, 18[15?] Jan 3 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    Signed by Timothy Dwight (1752-1817)
  - Certificate of admission to the Court of Chancery, New York State, 1815 Nov 15 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Passport issued by the Légation Américaine, Paris, 1821 Apr 21
  - Manuscript copy of "The Culprit Fay" [by Joseph Rodman Drake], bound vol., 1825 Aug 4 (Box 2, Folder 51)
    Flyleaf inscribed "Theodore Dwight, Jr., September 1846;" title page "Miss E. Boyd, August 4th, 1825;" with valentine to Theodore Dwight, Jr, "from M.E.P. or A.D.P.," 1846 Feb 14
  - Autograph album of Ellen Boyd Dwight, 1823-1855 (Box 2, Folder 52)
    Contains sketch of Newstead Abbey
  - Covers of book labeled "Fort Dummer Papers from Theodore Dwight's Collection, 62 Harrison St, Brooklyn", [after 1850] (Box 2, Folder 53)
    Papers of Timothy Dwight (1694-1771) were glued into this book, which seems to have been the geography book of Rebecca Dwight; the front endpaper is inscribed with what seem to be diary entries for a few days in June 1850
    See also: Series I, Papers of Timothy Dwight (1694-1771)
- Other Dwight Family Papers, 1711-1834; Series III; 8
  - Dwight, Nathaniel, copy of a letter to Habijah Savage, 1711 Apr 23 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Dwight, Sereno and Cynthia, two ALS to Mary Edwards Dwight, 1783 Feb 2, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Treat, Jn., ALS to Captain Henry Porter, 1787 May 4 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Wolcott, Oliver, ALS to Theodore Dwight (1764-1846), 1804 Apr 2 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Dwight, Timothy, ALS to Theodore Dwight (1764-1846), 1834 Feb 20 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Genealogies of the Dwight Family, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 59)